one of the courses I teach in the
cognitive science program is cognitive
250 which is the introduction to
cognitive science and I'm going to try
and compress the first sort of six weeks
of lecture into ten minutes so we'll see
how well that goes so what is cognitive
science and very often you get sort of
this thing from the catalog well it's
the interdisciplinary study of the
nature of cognition but why why
interdisciplinary well that has to do
with a little bit of the history so
we've been trying to understand the mind
and cognition for a long time and you
know philosophy I did quite a bit of
work at it but we realized that in
addition to that conceptual work we had
to do some experimental work where we
were studying more carefully behavior
and so psychology also starts to study
the the nature of the mind but we start
to realize that we can't study that just
on its own we need to understand the
brain level how is the brain causing and
contributing to behavior and that's
where of course neuroscience comes in
but it also matters how brains link up
to each other and so we need linguistics
and we need anthropology to also tell us
how mind and brains work so what we need
is these various disciplines to work
together in order to get a complete
picture because what matters is no one
of these levels is sufficient for
understanding the mind therefore no one
of these disciplines because all of
these levels are very causally
interdependent with each other they
affect each other the brain level
affects behavior behavior affects the
brain right the behavioral level right
for one brain is affected by the
behavior of other brains so that
anthropological cultural level or that
linguistic communicative level matters
and so what we need is we need a
discipline that isn't doing each one of
these levels but the discipline about
how they're causally interdependent and
therefore theoretically relevant to each
other
that's what cognitive science is and
cognitive science is therefore pursuing
a project of synaptic integration it is
trying to create a conceptual vocabulary
a theoretical grammar for how these
various disciplines can talk to each
other so as to afford this very valuable
synoptic integration
so that means that cognitive science is
this really creative project we're
trying to come up with these theoretical
constructs that will serve this
important purpose so what do you do when
you construct a theoretical construct
well what you do is you're trying to
make the most plausible construct you
can see what do I mean by plausibility I
want a theoretical construct that is
holds good promise that it's going to
predict where I'm going to find good
empirical evidence I want to I want a
construct that's going to help guide and
constrain future empirical research so I
need plausible constructs well how do we
come up with plausibility
in general well I'm going to indicate to
you a model of plausibility that I'm
working on with Leo Ferrara and this
plausibility model looks something like
this there's a couple things we're doing
to try and increase the plausibility of
our constructs the first thing we're
doing is we're trying to get convergence
we're trying to get how the various
disciplines various theoretical lines of
argument various empirical lines of
research all converge on a shared
conclusion why do we do that why does
that matter because when you get
convergence you increased
trustworthiness trustworthiness is the
is the conclusion that your construct
has not been produced by bias look I can
look at the book but in order to make
sure that the book is really there that
I can trust my perception I also reach
out and touch this book on neural
computing because if both my sight and
my touch converge on this it's less
likely that I'm just hallucinating the
book that it's just being produced by
bias it's much more likely that there's
something really there now is it perfect
no but it increases the probability that
the conclusion here that is resulting is
not due from any by any single line of
bias but from something really there but
I want something more than convergence
because what I want is I want to help
afford insight I want to indicate new
ways of thinking help people in the
various disciplines to solve problems to
open up new lines of research I need to
promise insight so one of the things my
constructs have to do right is they not
only have to have convergence for
trustworthiness
my constructs have to right be elegant
in the sense that I can use the same
construct in many different situations
so this is a highly powerful or
insightful construct because I can take
it here and frame and solve problems I
couldn't solve before here here here and
if the various disciplines can share
this construct this is one a powerful
way of affording synoptic integration
and I want a balance between these the
more I'm trying to transform the field
with my insight the more I need to
guarantee or at least assure myself that
my construct has high trustworthiness
because if I do this without ruling bias
I get weirdness I get conspiracy
theories I get fantasy I get craziness
right but if I have a lot of convergence
a lot of trustworthiness with a lot of
insight then I get triviality I get what
is obvious what everybody already knows
and that's also not scientifically
useful but if I can get something that's
highly convergent and highly elegant in
this manner then has a high degree of
plausibility then I have something
powerful potentially profoundly powerful
so cognitive science is about creating
these constructs
you